A Finding Aid to the Lucy R. Lippard Papers, 1930s-2007, bulk 1960s-1990, in the Archives of American Art AAA.lipplucy
Archives of American Art
Lucy R. Lippard papers
bulk 1960-1990
1930s-2007
AAA.lipplucy
Archives of American Art
53.3 Linear feet
The papers of New York writer, art critic, curator, and teacher, Lucy R. Lippard, measure 53.3 linear feet and date from the 1930s to 2007, with the bulk of the material dating from the 1960s to the 1990s. Over half of the collection consists of correspondence files documenting Lippard's professional relationships with artists, writers, galleries, art institutions, and political organizations, and her interest in conceptual and minimalist art, feminism and political activism. Also found are Lippard's notes and writings including sound recordings and interviews, teaching and exhibition files, printed material, several works of art, and photographs of artwork and artists. Scattered throughout the collection are a small number of records concerning Lippard's personal life.
Lippard, Lucy R.
Biographical/Historical note
New York writer, curator, art critic, and teacher, Lucy R. Lippard (1937-) is the curator of numerous exhibitions and the author of 20 books and other writings that trace the emergence of minimalist, post-minimalist, and conceptual art and document Lippard's committment to feminism and political activism.
Born in New York City in 1937, Lippard earned a B.A. from Smith college in 1958 and a M.A. in 1962 from New York University's Institute of Fine Arts. In the 1960s she began writing art criticism for the journals Art International and Artforum. In 1966 she curated the landmark "Eccentric Abstraction" exhibition at the Fischbach Gallery in New York City which established the standard for what would be considered post-minimalist art. Lippard then curated the first of four defining conceptual art exhibitions that became known as her "numbers shows," each titled after the populations of the cities in which they took place, with catalogs in the form of a set of 10 x 15 cm index cards. Opening at the Seattle Art Museum in 1969, "557,087" was followed by "955,000" in Vancouver, Canada, a few months later. "2,972,453" was held at the Centro de Arte y Comunicacíon in Buenos Aires in 1971 and "c.7500" opened in Valencia, California, in 1973-1974 before traveling to several other venues in the United States and Europe.
Lippard's first book, The Graphic Work of Philip Evergood was published in 1966, followed by Pop Art the same year. Six Years: The Dematerialization of the Art Object (1973) and From the Center: Feminist Essays on Women's Art (1976) documented the emergence of conceptual art and the early years of feminist art respectively. In 1976 Lippard published her seminal book on the life and work of Eva Hesse.
Between 1977 and 1978 Lippard lived on a farm in Devon, England, intending to write a novel. During her walks across the English countryside she became interested in landscape art and conceived of her book Overlay: Contemporary Art and the Art of Prehistory which was subsequently published in 1983. Other books include Get the Message?: A Decade Of Art For Social Change (1984), Ad Reinhardt (1985), and Mixed Blessings: New Art in a Multicultural America (1990). Lippard has also written regular columns on art and politics for the Village Voice, In These Times and Z Magazine, and has been a contributing editor of Art in America.
Lippard was radicalized during a trip to Argentina in 1968 when she was invited to be a juror at the Museo Nacional de Bellas Artes in Buenos Aires. On her return to the United States she became heavily involved in anti-war activities and the Art Workers Coalition. She is a co-founder of several feminist and artist organizations including the feminist collective Heresies, which produced Heresies: A Feminist Journal on Art and Politics from 1977-1992, Ad Hoc Women Artists, Alliance for Cultural Democracy, Artists Call Against U.S. Intervention in Central America, Artists Meeting for Cultural Change, Women's Action Coalition, and Women's Art Registry. In 1976 she was a founder of Printed Matter, a New York nonprofit dedicated to producing publications by artists. She also worked closely with Franklin Furnace, an artist-run space devoted to the promotion of artists' books, installation art, and video and performance art, and served on the organization's International Committee.
Lippard has been a visiting professor at the School of Visual Arts, the University of Colorado, Boulder, and the University of Queensland, Australia. She has received honorary doctorates in fine arts from Maine College of Art, the Massachusetts College of Art, Moore College of Art, and San Francisco Art Institute, as well as awards including a Guggenheim Fellowship, two National Endowment for the Arts grants in criticism, the Smith College Medal and the ArtTable Award for Distinguished Service to the Visual Arts.
Lippard has lived in New Mexico since 1992 and continues to work as a freelance writer and speaker.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of New York writer, art critic, curator, and teacher, Lucy R. Lippard, measure 53.3 linear feet and date from the 1930s to 2007, with the bulk of the material dating from the 1960s to the 1990s. Over half of the collection consists of correspondence files documenting Lippard's professional relationships with artists, writers, galleries, art institutions, and political organizations, and her interest in conceptual and minimalist art, feminism and political activism. Also found are Lippard's notes and writings including sound recordings and interviews, teaching and exhibition files, printed material, several works of art, and photographs of artwork and artists. Scattered throughout the collection are a small number of records concerning Lippard's personal life.
A small amount of biographical material comprises resumes and an address book.
Correspondence files document all aspects of Lippard's professional life including her relatiohnships with artists such as Carl Andre, Judy Chicago, Hanne Darboven, Ray Johnson, Sol LeWitt, and Henry Pearson; feminist artists including Mary Beth Edelson, Harmony Hammond, Donna Henes, and May Stevens; political and art-related activist groups such as Alliance for Cultural Democracy, Art Workers Coalition, Political Art Documentation/Distrubution, Printed Matter, and Women's Caucus for Art; galleries and museums including Addison Gallery of American Art and the Museum of Modern Art, and publishers including Art International and Art Forum. The series also traces the development of Lippard's involvement in activist causes including censorship and the rights of artists, Central America and the impact of U.S. policy on the region, and equality and reproductive rights for women, as well as her interest in conceptual, minimalist and post-minimalist art. The series includes scattered artwork and photographs of artists.
Writings are primarily by Lippard and include correspondence, manuscript drafts, extensive notes, and publication records for some of her best-known books such as The Graphic Work of Philip Evergood (1966), Six Years: The Dematerialization of the Art Object (1973), Eva Hesse (1976), Ad Reinhardt (1985), and Mixed Blessings: New Art in a Multicultural America (1990), as well as essays for publications such as Art Forum and Studio International and contributions to exhibition catalogs. Also found are edited transcripts from conferences, symposia and interviews conducted by and of Lippard, some audio recordings of interviews and symposia, including an interview with Donald Judd, and notes and typescripts for lectures and speeches.
A small number of files document Lippard's teaching work during the 1970s and 1980s, primarily at the University of Colorado, Boulder where she taught several courses and seminars.
Exhibition files document Lippard's involvement with exhibitions she helped to organize or curate such as "A Different War: Vietnam in Art" (1989-1991) "557,087" and "955,000" (1969, 1970), "2,972, 453" (1971) "c.7,500" (1973-1974) and those for which she wrote catalog contributions.
Printed material includes a collection of articles written by Lippard and a small amount of material concerning events, such as speaking engagements, in which Lippard was involved. Other printed material reflects Lippard's wide range of artistic, political and activist interests and documents exhibitions and performances and the activities of art-related and political groups. Material includes many exhibition catalogs, announcements, invitations, printed posters, news clippings, journal articles, brochures, pamphlets and other publications.
Artwork includes 16 items by unidentified artists, including 2 by children. Photographs consist primarily of photographs of works of art in addition to a small number of photos of exhibition installations.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as eight series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1960s-circa 1980s (Box 1; 2 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1950s-2006 (Boxes 1-28, 51, OVs 54-63; 28.8 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, 1930s-1990s (Boxes 28-41, 51-52, OVs 64-66; 13.24 linear feet)
Series 4: Teaching Files, 1966-1993 (Boxes 41, 52; 0.76 linear feet)
Series 5: Exhibitions, 1960s-1990s (Boxes 42-45, 52, OVs 67-68; 4.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1940s-2007 (Boxes 45-49, 52, OVs 69-77; 5.3 linear feet)
Series 7: Artwork and Ephemera, circa 1960s-circa 1990s (Boxes 50, 53; 4 folders)
Series 8: Photographs, 1950s-circa 1990s (Boxes 50, 53, OV 71; 1.0 linear foot)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Lucy R. Lippard donated her papers in several increments between 1972-1995, and 2006.
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Lucy Lippard conducted in 2011 March 15, by Sue Heinemann, for the Archives of American Art's Elizabeth Murray Oral History of Women in the Visual Arts project, funded by a grant from the A G Foundation.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Christo, 1935-; Edelson, Mary Beth; Evergood, Philip, 1901-1973; Hesse, Eva, 1936-1970; Johnson, Ray, 1927-; Judd, Donald, 1928-; Lewitt, Sol, 1928-; Long, Richard, 1945-; Oldenburg, Claes, 1929-; Reinhardt, Ad, 1913-1967; Smith, Tony, 1912-; Art criticism--New York (State)--New York; Art critics; Art, Modern--20th century; Art--Study and teaching; Artists--Political activity; Curators--New York (State)--New York; Exhibition catalogs; Interviews; Photographs; Sound recordings; Works of art
- Biographical Material, circa 1960s-circa 1980s; Series 1; 2 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Resumes summarize Lippard's professional acheivements and an address book includes a list of birthdays, as well as addresses and phone numbers of a large number of Lippard's colleagues, family and friends.
  - Resumes, circa 1960s-circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Address Book, 1967-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1950s-2006; Series 2; 28.8 Linear feet Boxes 1-28, 51, OVs 54-63
  Correspondence forms the bulk of the collection and is between Lippard and artists, writers, galleries, art institutions and organizations, educational institutions, political organizations, and publishers. Also found is a small amount of personal and family correspondence. The bulk of the correspondence is incoming with scattered copies of Lippard's outgoing replies.
  In addition to correspondence and notes, the series includes a significant amount of printed matter, such as clippings, journals, exhibition catalogs and announcements, and scattered publications of the Mail Art network, photographic material including photographs of artwork and artists, and original artwork found in some of the artist's files.
  The series also includes recordings on 7 sound tape reels and 18 sound cassettes.
  Arrangement note
  Lippard appears to have sorted incoming mail into very rough alphabetical order prior to donation, generally mixing correspondence with files that could more accurately be described as subject or reference files. Although the latter primarily consist of photographic and/or printed material, the basic alphabetical arrangement of the creator has been maintained and sorted into 2 subseries. All correspondents and subjects with 4 or more related items are housed in a named file; all other items are housed in a "General" file at the end of the file group for the appropriate letter of the alphabet.
  2.1: Correspondence by Name, 1950s-2006
  2.2: Correspondence by Subject, 1950s-1990s
  - Correspondence by Name, 1950s-2006; 2.1
    The series documents all aspects of Lippards professional life, primarily from the 1960s on, including her relationship with artists such as Carl Andre, Iain Baxter (N. E. Thing Co.), Bruce Barber, Carole Berge, Steve Cagan, Don Celender, Judy Chicago, Hanne Darboven, Ken Friedman, Donna Henes, Hera, Alexis Hunter, Ray Johnson, Joseph Kossuth, Sol LeWitt, Martha Rosler, Henry Pearson, Arthur and Irene Siegel, Tal Streeter, Bill Vazan and many more. Lippard's interest in and committment to the emerging feminist art scene can be traced in correspondence with artists such as Joan Braderman, Mary Beth Edelson, Harmony Hammond, Ruth Hardinger, Elizabeth Hess, Miriam Schapiro, May Stevens and Merle Temkin, many of whom, along with Lippard, were founding members of the New York-based Heresies Collective.
    Also found here is correspondence and other material documenting Lippard's involvement with art galleries, art instutions and activist groups including Addison Gallery of American Art, Alliance for Cultural Democracy, and Political Art Documentation/Distribution (PAD/D). PAD/D material consists of 11 audio recordings from circa 1984 related to "Artists Call Against U.S. Intervention in Central America" and other activities of the group. Eight folders document the founding and early years of the Women's Caucus for Art from the early 1970s to 1981 and the series includes Lippard's correspondence with related individuals and organizations such as Arlene Raven, Sheila de Bretteville and the College Art Association. Records on the Art Workers Coalition (AWC) and the Museum of Modern Art document Lippard's involvement in the AWC's artists' rights protests aimed at pressurizing the Museum of Modern Art and other museums to implement certain reforms, including a weekly free admission day.
    Correspondence with Ray Johnson includes original letters from Johnson to Lippard and many examples of his mail art. A folder of letters from Christo and Jean-Claude includes a letter illustrated with sketches of artwork that had impressed Christo at a University of British Columbia art show and describing a meeting with Ray Johnson. Six folders of correspondence from Hanne Darboven are interspersed with her distinctive colors, dashes, numbers and wavy lines and letters and postcards from Sol LeWitt include sketches and descriptions of artwork.
    Lippard corresponded with many artists outside the United States, including Australian artists Vivienne Binns and Peter Kennedy, and New Zealand artist Bruce Barber, and wrote an article for Arts Canada on the Canadian group Pulsa. Her interest in landscape art can be traced in her correspondence with artists such as Bill Vazan and British artist Richard Long.
    There are 4 folders of correspondence between Lippard and James (Jim) Fitzimmons regarding her work for the publication Art International during the 1960s, and two folders of correspondence with publisher Harry N. Abrams, Inc., but the bulk of the correspondence related to Lippard's writings can be found in Series 3.1. Other writers with whom Lippard corresponded include New York art critic Frederick Ted Castle, artist and writer Judy Loeb, writer and storyteller Gioia Timpanelli and Argentine-born critic Susana Torre, who designed the cover for Lippard's book From the Center: Feminist Essays on Women's Art (1976).
    The series includes one folder each of correspondence from Lippard's parents Margaret Lippard and Vernon W. Lippard.
    Sound recordings are on 7 sound tape reels and 17 sound cassettes.
    - A.I.R. Gallery, 1996; 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Abakamowicz, Magdalene, circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Includes phots of Abakamowicz
    - Abish, Cecile and Walter, circa 1971-circa 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Acconci, Vito, circa 1969-circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Acconci, Vito, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Acconci, Vito, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Oversized material housed in OV 54
    - Acconci, Vito, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Acconci, Vito, circa 1978-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ace Space Co., circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Ada, circa 1980-circa 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Adams, Alice, 1960s-1980s (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Adams & Goldbard (Adams, Don and Goldbard, Arlene), 1984-1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Adams, Mac, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Addison Gallery of American Art, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Addison Gallery of American Art, 1980-1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Alaska Design Forum, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Albers, Josef, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Allen, Francie, circa 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, circa 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, circa 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, circa 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Oversized material housed in Box 51, Folder 1
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, 1983 January-April (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, 1983 May-October (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, 1983 October (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, 1983 October-December (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Alliance for Cultural Democracy, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Allyn, Jerri, 1979-1993 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Amateau, Michèle, circa 1974-circa 1983 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - And/Or Gallery, Seattle, circa 1974-circa 1976 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Anderson, Laurie, circa 1979-circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Andre, Carl, circa 1973-circa 1992 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Anglesey, Zoe, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Antin, Eleanor, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Antioch University, 1975-1991 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Antonakos, Stephen, circa 1967-circa 1991 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Appalachian State University, 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Apple, Billy, circa 1971-circa 1972 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Applebroog, Ida, circa 1978-circa 1983 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Araeen, Rasheed, circa 1980-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Archaeological Conservancy, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Archives of American Art, circa 1967-circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Arizona State University, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Armajani, Siah, circa 1970 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Arnatt, Keith, circa 1967-circa 1972 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
      Includes photos of Arnatt; oversized material housed in OV 58
    - Art In America, circa 1970-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Art International (Jim Fitzimmons), circa 1964-circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
    - Art Workers Coalition, circa 1969-circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
    - Art Workers Coalition, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Art Workers Coalition, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 11-13)
    - Art Workers Coalition, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Art Workers Coalition, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Art Workers Coalition, Slide Show Discussion, Simon Frasier University (1969 Feb), 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Art Workers Coalition, 2nd Discussion Group, Alternatives Committee (1969 May 29), 1 sound tape reels (Box 2, Folder 17)
      The only attendee that is named in the recording is Lucy Lippard. Others present may include Robert Morris and Rudolph Baranik.
    - Art Workers Coalition, Open Hearing Tapes 1-2, circa 1960s; 2 sound tape reels (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Art Workers Coalition, Open Hearing Tapes 3-4, circa 1960s; 2 sound tape reels (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Artemesia, circa 1970s-1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Artes Visuales, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Artforum, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Artists Against the Expressway, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Artists Residents of Chicago (ARC), circa 1974-circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Arts Magazine, circa 1970-circa 1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - ArtsCanada, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Artschwager, Richard, circa 1967-circa 1969 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Asbury, Jane, circa 1975-circa 1977 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Aschenbrenner, Michael, circa 1981-circa 1991 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Ascher, Mary, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Asher, Michael, circa 1969-circa 1971 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Askevold, David, circa 1967-circa 1974 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Includes photo of Askevold
    - Atkinson, Conrad, 1990s (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Ault, Julie, 1984-1999 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Aycock, Alice, circa 1971-circa 1978 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Aylon, Helane, circa 1978-circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - A, General: A.-Adz, 1970s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - A, General: Af-Ak, 1970s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - A, General: Al-Am, 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - A, General: An, 1970s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - A, General: Ap-Arm, 1970s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - A, General: Art, 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - A, General: Arte-Arv, 1970s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - A, General: As, 1970s-2002 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - A, General: At-Az, 1950s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - A, First Names Only, 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - A, Illegible, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Baden, Mowry, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Oversized material housed in Box 51 Folder 1
    - Bail, Murray, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Baker, Betsy, 1966-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Baldessari, John, circa 1960s-circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - Balkind, Alvin, 1968-1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Baracks, Barbara, 1970s-1980 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Baranik, Rudolf, 1970s-1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Barber, Bruce, 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Includes photo of Barber; oversized material housed in OV 54
    - Barber, Pauline and Bruce, 1970s-1988 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Bardo, Arthur, circa 1960s-circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Barry, Judith, circa 1970s-circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Barry, Robert, circa 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Oversized material housed in OV 58
    - Barry, Robert, 1973-1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Barthelme, Rick, 1950s-1970s (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
    - Barthelme, Rick, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Bas, Jan Ader, 1970-1975 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Bates, Elizabeth, circa 1970s-circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Baumann, Jim, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Becher, Bernard and Hilla, 1970s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Beckley, Bill, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Beebe, Mary L. (Portland Center for Visual Arts), circa 1970s-circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Beens, Olivia, 1983-1990 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Benglis, Lynda, 1970s-circa 1990 (Box 3, Folder 25)